[SPEAKER_02]: Is this the word change?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm more interested in... more about the arising and the passing, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: We were talking about the... so, the experience as a whole, imagining, like, say, the feeling that's present, that's enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that seems like something that, you know, everyone can discern.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the Buddha talks about people contemplating arising and passing for all five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that kind of makes you sort of think, okay, so, you know, you can recognize
[SPEAKER_01]: The arising of a mood, or you can recognize that a mood is arising, but maybe it's not quite so straightforward to recognize what's meant by the arising of matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, another way of approaching it would be the senses, the body, arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like,
[SPEAKER_02]: It's somewhere where the Buddha says... Well, before you go too far, the... What is the most... What is the closest matter to you?
[SPEAKER_02]: The body.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is the... What is the closest sense perception to you?
[SPEAKER_02]: The eye.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, okay, so what is the I?
[SPEAKER_02]: On the level of what is the I?
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you have the I without having the body?
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you just have the I without the body?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the body, again, on the basis of the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you have a presently enduring mood?
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever the mood is, pleasant, unpleasant, neutral, without your body being there, alive.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not so.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hence, you want to contemplate the rising and ceasing of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's going on?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want to get involved.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want to contemplate the arising and ceasing of the five aggregates, you need to contemplate the arising and ceasing of the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not like when people think, oh, what is the arising of the matter?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Means, you you are not contemplating it, you are abstracting it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, first you have to discern what the matter is that's closest to you, as in the only matter you can really even indirectly experience, which is this body.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, if matter is to be understood, it's to be understood on the level of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And everything else is discerned through that, because I can only...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can only recognize, you know, we talk about sort of external things, the dog over there, but that's always me sitting here, my eyes...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, that's already on the basis of your body.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you trying to understand something without having understood the base of your body, means that won't be applying to the right thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It won't be understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you mentioned it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Get back.
[SPEAKER_01]: Describe it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Describe the I.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when I ask, when I ask, what is, what is I?
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the I?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you say that, first thing, first thing you sort of consider is what I'm seeing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, you know, I see you sitting there, which kind of...
[SPEAKER_02]: Right, look,
[SPEAKER_02]: For yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you say, my eye is like this, or this eye, or that eye, what do you refer to?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's only in relation to what I'm seeing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So... Yeah, well, no, see, that's like when you infer afterwards, how did you get to know it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, well, I'm asking you, what are you...
[SPEAKER_02]: I can't, like, that's the thing, I can't, I can't... You can talk about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what are you talking about?
[SPEAKER_02]: What is that thing?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that thing, it's not like, oh, I am, when I say the I, I refer to the negative aspect of the positive seeing, da-da-da-da-da.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, that's all your rationalization afterwards.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you say, oh, can you give me this?
[SPEAKER_02]: I need to cover my eyes.
[SPEAKER_02]: What are those eyes that you talk about?
[SPEAKER_02]: How do you regard that thing?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it for you?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the significance of it for you?
[SPEAKER_01]: This.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: These two.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing too complex, nothing too difficult.
[SPEAKER_01]: Two blocks of flesh in front of my face.
[SPEAKER_02]: What are the further characteristics?
[SPEAKER_02]: Describe it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Talk about the two lumps of flesh.
[SPEAKER_01]: What else is there revealed through the two lumps of flesh?
[SPEAKER_01]: That the particular bit of the body, which gets called the eye, which I have to call the eye, which seems to be kind of... which I can close, and then I don't see anything, which I can... You don't really close it, you just cover it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So there's still sort of a vague seeing that goes on when my eyes are closed, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You still see kind of hints.
[SPEAKER_02]: So does that mean... can you...
[SPEAKER_02]: Interfere, or can you prevent the eye from seeing?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just by closing my eyes, I can't stop myself from seeing, because I can still see pink, I can see light, I can see... Light, accents of light, all those things are seen.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the two lumps of flesh in your face, that are your eyes, the organs of the eyes, you can't actually command them, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't decide when to
[SPEAKER_01]: The center of, or the root of, the whole domain within which things appear in that kind of way, a very different way from the, like, say, the hearing domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that whole domain is just...
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't...
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't choose it for it to be there, and I can't stop it from being there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, the the choice that you can exercise over the organs, lumps of flesh of your eyes, is the choice within that domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can choose not to look at this, to look at something else, but you have no choice about looking at the domain of seeing you are subjected to.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what would then be the characteristics of something that you are subjected to and have no say about?
[SPEAKER_02]: How would you describe that experience?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, sort of, I have no fundamental control here.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the thing, though.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, recognizing that any level of control is like choosing to look at that
[SPEAKER_01]: That you're subjected to the domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can only choose one particular choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: What I'm asking you now is, what are the characteristics of being subjected to something or anything?
[SPEAKER_02]: How does that feel?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I guess it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: Being subjected to things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if things are not necessarily unpleasant, the fact that you do not say, on that fundamental level, that you're subjected to
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, but it's being vertebrate, it's being subjected to it, being overwhelmed by it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if everything is pleasant in your eyes, in your sound, in all the senses, the fact is that...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like I was hit by it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: The fact is that because it's pleasant, there is always the implicit possibility of it ceasing to be pleasant or becoming otherwise.
[SPEAKER_02]: And all that stems from that very
[SPEAKER_02]: Fundamental relationship with those things, which is that you are subjected to them, not that they are subjected to your will.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if it's pleasant, the fact that I was subjected to it means that I didn't choose for that pleasure to arise, which means it could not arise.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's more than enough for the basis of suffering to manifest, more than enough for dukkha to show itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: The real pleasure, then, it's not in experiencing pleasure and not experiencing pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: The true pleasure, as in the agreeability of experience, is when you are in control.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you were in control.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you are the one who is sort of subjecting things, not subjected to them.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the good news is, that's possible.
[SPEAKER_02]: As the Buddha said, like in case of an arahant, he said, his mind doesn't overwhelm him, he overwhelms his mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: But now you need to understand how that's done.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, he doesn't overwhelm his mind through the power of will, because power of will is secondary, already within the domain of the senses, including the domain of the mind, as we described it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the only way to then, you not be overwhelmed by the mind, and you overwhelm the mind, is to fully relinquish the ownership of the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Fully relinquish the ownership of that which is necessarily
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what is that thing that needs to be abandoned, that is liable to things that are not in your control?
[SPEAKER_01]: What are the characteristics of the sense of self?
[SPEAKER_01]: Describe it.
[SPEAKER_01]: How does it feel?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I was thinking about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, in terms of feeling, it's like... it's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like that second arrow.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like the kind of... there's a... it's like a response to... so there's a feeling already there, but then there's also... there's also other feelings on top of that, that are kind of a response to that original feeling, like not wanting it to be there or, you know, like wanting pleasure, not wanting pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, yeah, there's sort of domain of feelings that are involved in trying to manage your feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: But how does the sense of self then?
[SPEAKER_02]: What are the characteristics of the sense of self in regard to that?
[SPEAKER_01]: That seems to be... that seems to be... that's like...
[SPEAKER_02]: When you say, when you say, I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, I am so-and-so.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is that I am bit?
[SPEAKER_02]: The name of the nāma, what does that refer to?
[SPEAKER_01]: What are you designating with it?
[SPEAKER_01]: I can say my point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can say...
[SPEAKER_02]: But is that explicitly present when you talk about I am?
[SPEAKER_02]: That point of view is right there?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, exactly, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what is right there?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not like what you think should be there or what you find when you start looking closer.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you just casually, carelessly say, I am this or I am that, what are you referring to with that I am?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if there is truly nothing, it would be unintelligible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a whole set of... so, it's a whole kind of various assumptions of, you know... Again, when you introduce variety, it can only be secondary.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what is the thing you're referring to when you say, I am?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the reason why you kind of...
[SPEAKER_02]: That which is dear.
[SPEAKER_02]: What are the characteristics of something being dear to you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Find pleasurable and care about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you sort of have... you keep having this sense of, like, wanting to control it somehow, because you don't want bad to come to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is the implication of that in everything that you find dear.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you realize that
[SPEAKER_02]: Could you have such an implication of control without assuming at least a possibility of ownership over it?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, say, you say, like, somebody, someone, your loved ones, and you...
[SPEAKER_01]: Your loved ones.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You basically, when I say that, and you find them dear, you think, well, I don't want anything bad to come of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: As if I can, somehow,
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, you could see the thread.
[SPEAKER_02]: They were just kind of revealed.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you say, I am so-and-so, you refer to certain generality of your experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you can say, I am this and that.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's you rationalizing afterwards.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the moment of designation, when you're speaking,
[SPEAKER_02]: What you're referring to is that kind of a generally present experience as a whole, that's enduring there.
[SPEAKER_02]: But yes, there are certain characteristics that are implied in you designating it with I am, unless your mind is enlightened, in which, as the Buddha said, even Tathāgata uses words like I am, this and this is mine, without those things really meaning that, implying the ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you're not the Tathāgata, means there is a degree of ownership implied in those things.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the first thing people do is, there is no I am then.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no I.
[SPEAKER_02]: Deny it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Deny everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, you deny the problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, there is no problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: The fact that you can still speak in terms of I am this or I'm not this, means there is still the implication of that generality that endures for you that you are designating as yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's exactly the point.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't have the sense of I am without sense of mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't have the sense of I am, however vague, however careless, without the sense of ownership of that general experience that endures there for you, that you are subjected to, not subjected to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, when you're referring to I am, you're implying the ownership of your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, if you say, okay, police the language, stop saying I am, because the Buddha said anatta, you're still regarding... you can... you can... Now, something else, a different designation, will take its place.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's the underlying view that makes you assume the ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, your language sort of replicates it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you're saying I am,
[SPEAKER_02]: You look at it as a symptom of, is there the underlying ownership of my attitude?
[SPEAKER_02]: Not in terms of, oh, I must stop saying that because that's not Buddhist or something like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there is no sense of I am without the sense of ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, if you want to really develop the experience of anatta, it's not about saying there is no self.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's basically about abandoning the ownership of that which you are designating as your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what would be then, what would the characteristics of the ownership be?
[SPEAKER_02]: Characteristics in general.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: Of mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Belongs to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Belonging to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Could belong to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having this thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's another thing, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't have.
[SPEAKER_02]: You would not entertain the sense of owning something if there is no implicit pleasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Non-threat.
[SPEAKER_02]: Familiarity.
[SPEAKER_02]: All those things are rooted in pleasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't look at it, you know, like, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: You suddenly notice you've got someone leech on you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like it's... you don't think, oh, that's mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or cancer.
[SPEAKER_02]: That which is yours, body, but that's not yours because it's killing you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the alien on my body.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you say, my cancer, you really deep down, you want to get rid of the minus of the cancer.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the... that's the... that's the key.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, can you then take this reflection further?
[SPEAKER_02]: Sense of ownership, sense of mind, is a necessary basis for me entertaining the sense of I am, as my own, belonging to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you were to then fully understand the sense of ownership, there is a good chance you'll be able to then not entertain the sense of I am on the basis of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what are the characteristics and further characteristics of the sense of ownership?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, as the Buddha said, regarding things as mine,
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a meaningless mistake.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's nevertheless the mistake.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how do you rectify the mistake?
[SPEAKER_02]: What is it that you regard as yours?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, when you regard something as mine, what are the characteristics of that thing?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, yeah, I mean, just sort of asking the same question.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well... Can you say this is mine without this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you say mine?
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's always in relation to a thing that's already given.
[SPEAKER_02]: It has to be something that's yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, which is first then?
[SPEAKER_02]: The thing that's given.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it your sense of mind comes first and then finds things for its ownership?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that sense of ownership is secondary to, is completely dependent upon, a thing which happens to be given in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is on the level of how we started this?
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, the particular sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, but the domain of those senses, it's pretty much already inaccessible to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's given your subjectivity.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, your sense of ownership then cannot possibly step outside of that domain, of any of those domains.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's fully within.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, is then that truly can be called...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, fully understanding that, you see that any sense of ownership I can possibly have towards any of this, is always going to be dependent upon...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's only a relative ownership, on account of things they were given that you don't own, and relative ownership
[SPEAKER_02]: Because relative ownership, it's not ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not your ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like recognizing a relative degree of control you have within the domain that you have no control over.
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess just seeing that, actually, just how... Well, repetitively seeing what you've just done.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why the suttas would go into these repetitions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not like because they were repetitive for the sake of repetition itself, but because each repetition, it's a phenomenological description of how should your understanding unravel.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's not about figuring it out, like, oh, yeah, I got it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's about constantly reapplying the same figuring out on every possible or every relevant level.
[SPEAKER_02]: In case of the senses, it's the six relevant levels.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you have to keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you don't do it, it's enough to just ignore a certain level and assume that you know what you already know.
[SPEAKER_02]: And to that extent, you are not free of that assumption.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, sure, you need to understand the principle to begin with, in order to know what to apply, as in, as we just described, the principle of non-ownership is more fundamental than principle of ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ownership is secondary to it, the right order of things.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then it needs to be done repetitively, in regard to the body, in regard to senses, in regard to whichever way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Look at the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's do the mind now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Isn't it re-adjusting your point of view?
[SPEAKER_00]: Carry on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, seeing where that point of view actually is, in regard to things, rather than... because self assumes a point of view which is beyond things that are happening.
[SPEAKER_00]: In its direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right, right.
[SPEAKER_02]: I see.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what you mean by it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how would you do it?
[SPEAKER_02]: And how would you describe that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, by seeing that those... that point of view is surrounded by things happening to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's... Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: But let's... let's do it like... let's do how we've done this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your point of view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just... and stop the sentence there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, point of view, point of view.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is the point of view?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what suttas do, by the way, when the monks exclaim things twice.
[SPEAKER_02]: First jhāna, first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is first jhāna?
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, I stop...
[SPEAKER_02]: I won't think about things that relate to first jhāna until I understand the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whatever you want to understand, that's how to start.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm designating something.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm throwing this thing in this direction, without being concerned with any other direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: What it is that I'm aiming at?
[SPEAKER_02]: It is that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when you say point of view, describe that... that phenomena you're designating by calling it point
[SPEAKER_02]: What are the characteristics of that point of view?
[SPEAKER_00]: You're the center of experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: The center of experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's quite an accurate description in a way.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, what are the characteristics of that center of that experience further?
[SPEAKER_02]: Have you created it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or have you just found it there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it is... it is... it is part of the structure already that's there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, can you, like, for example, if you have doubt, or have I created it, can you remove it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you exercise your will to say, no more of this center?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, even the point of view shares the same characteristics as this I-domain, E-domain, domain of dhamma, domain of the arisen phenomena.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how you stop assuming the outside point of view, by seeing that point of view, point of view, oh, I have no control over this.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when you think outside of the point of view, that's already within the horizon structure, as you called it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's...
[SPEAKER_02]: The external point of view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, the external point of view of ātavāda, it's not actually external in its content.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's only external to the extent you ignore that it cannot be external.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, take ātavāda, ātavāda.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is ātavāda?
[SPEAKER_02]: Self-view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Translate it whichever way you want.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or don't translate it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Use the Pali.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then think about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: What does it refer to?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, it refers to the self that's independent of the five hundreds.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, you're describing and there is a phenomenon there enduring for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And apply the same principle for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: The external point of view, the external point of view, external to what?
[SPEAKER_02]: Then you realize the extern... external aspect of it, externalness, is only relatively external to the content of something else.
[SPEAKER_02]: Independent, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then you realize, oh, so it's not truly external.
[SPEAKER_02]: And not thinking that, clearly, not clarifying that fully, you maintain the notion that it's truly external, that I'm truly independent.
[SPEAKER_00]: It isn't also that things are happening to me, within me, in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things are happening within my point of view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's secondary.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not saying that's the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, that's the truth of... Sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I'm saying that even in that case, in order to address that, you need to see that point of view first, correctly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, there will be no division in a sense of in me, outside of me, in that fundamental sense of...
[SPEAKER_02]: When there is.
[SPEAKER_02]: When there is, your starting point is then, things are happening to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: To what?
[SPEAKER_02]: To this center of experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: What are the characteristics of the center of experience?
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, now, that's going into actually trying to understand it, that as a... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...someone who doesn't understand it, that's what it's like.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's...
[SPEAKER_02]: But what about that?
[SPEAKER_02]: How's that relevant then?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, to know what it's like.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if you're not trying to understand it... Yeah, but you are busy.
[SPEAKER_00]: To understand it, you have to know what it's like.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's not relevant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's still the point.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, if you are trying to understand it, or you won't understand it, any of those divisions in me, outside of me, happening to me,
[SPEAKER_02]: That's all fine, but if you want to understand it, you have to go beyond it, because all of those divisions that you talk about, are the result of you already appropriating the point of view, which you can't.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you look at it closely, it becomes impossible to appropriate it, because it has a reason on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're saying that only once you've understood it, can you understand what ignorance was?
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: In hindsight.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't understand what ignorance is while you're still ignorant of that ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's exactly the point I was making.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, trying to understand it, you start revealing what's going on, which happens to be an ignorant thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: However, it's important, as we've done there before as well, to clarify that revealing what's going on can often become psychologizing for people.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, in general, people think that if I just start talking about this, I'm revealing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: You must stay with the first phenomenon you started to designate and understand that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, when you take that further, understand the next one.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why I say, like, oh, so point of view is the center of my experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Wait.
[SPEAKER_02]: Point of view, point of view.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is the point of view?
[SPEAKER_02]: Describe the characteristics.
[SPEAKER_02]: You've done so?
[SPEAKER_02]: Put it aside.
[SPEAKER_02]: Center of experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: What are the characteristics of that?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's how you get to undo your ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not by figuring it out on account of ignorant premises, but by questioning every single premise that you started with.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, yeah, you would then understand how you were ignorant before.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if I say, it feels like things are happening within me, and I've got to clarify each... That's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like, oh, you shouldn't say that.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's absolutely right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Things that, like, describe your experience, oh, it feels like things are happening in me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: In me.
[SPEAKER_02]: What are the characteristics of that?
[SPEAKER_02]: How does that feel?
[SPEAKER_02]: Things happening in you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Say, something's happening in you.
[SPEAKER_02]: How would you...?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, actually, you surround the things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Carry on.
[SPEAKER_00]: In me, means that things are happening in me, that I am surrounded, I surround those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, think of an example.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, just my... everything is happening.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think the most obvious example for people would be thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thoughts are in my head.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thoughts are in me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I'm thinking more even with what I'm seeing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, well, take any example you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is my experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever is happening inside my head...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you're seeing now is happening inside you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Inside.
[SPEAKER_02]: Inside.
[SPEAKER_02]: My experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that entails, that implies, then the opposite.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how can you experience that opposite?
[SPEAKER_02]: If everything you can experience is only inside of you.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, can then the opposite... can then the outside of you be experienced, if your own experience is always inside of you?
[SPEAKER_02]: How can you then know what's outside, unless you experience it inside, in which case it's not outside anymore?
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, when you think inside, you implicitly determine the outside.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's not this inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which you can't experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which you can't then experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, can there be inside without any outside that's inexperienceable?
[SPEAKER_02]: Then you realize it can't.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then you realize also that this inside is all you have.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, any division between inside and outside are on the inside.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's... that's...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm just going back to the...
[SPEAKER_00]: The basic experience is that self, then, is a thing which you don't look at, first of all, because it will fall apart.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is not seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Self is basically not under... For there to be a self,
[SPEAKER_00]: It needs to be not understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an ignorant, unseen thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which one assumes to be there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because as soon as you start looking in that direction... Yeah, but I'm still basically on the inside-outside.
[SPEAKER_02]: How does that connect to that then?
[SPEAKER_02]: The sense of self and the sense of inside?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because it implies that you are outside.
[SPEAKER_02]: The inside implies that you're outside, or the sense of self?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that I am beyond that which is inside.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, okay, yeah, you can start with that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, let's use that as a basis.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that is the characteristic, pretty much, of everything is happening to me, thus I am basically the outsides of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's implied instantly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your kind of... Well, that's exactly the kind of the characteristics of the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Indescribable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Eternal, lasting forever, non-dependent of these things.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't negate that, but you need to understand it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you won't understand it by kind of not... you won't understand it by thinking on the basis of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You will understand it by undoing the basis of it, as in the undoing the lack of understanding of the basis of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the experience of things are happening to me is fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's your starting point.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what is that, as we said, sense of me that we described?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, there's a sense of ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a sense of things are liable to these things happening.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, like, things are happening to this body, things are happening to the senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you get involved by assuming the ownership of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you start looking closely, you realize you have no control over the domain of eyes, no control over the domain of ears, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, if you were to remove then the ownership, you would then remove that equal self-centered sense of I am and this is happening to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you try to sort of figure out internally and externally and then how you relate to it, it won't be on the same fundamental level of undoing the premise of self that you took for granted.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's what I mean, like, when you describe, describe the sense of self, as we've just done.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you're already thinking, oh, sense of self needs to be figured out, sure, and it's happening to me, all of these divisions, all of these ways of thinking are already secondary to you have taken the ownership of it, and the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hence, every individual thing basically can then serve as a base for understanding the principle that would apply to whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you're not looking to understand the principle, then no amount of individual things can bring the kind of the whole picture.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's already secondary to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, things are happening to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not necessarily the best basis to start because
[SPEAKER_02]: Things are happening to me or not, doesn't really matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a bit abstract.
[SPEAKER_02]: Things are happening to me and I'm the sense of self in regard to...
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, but then I would ask you, why is that a problem?
[SPEAKER_02]: Presumably, whoever wants to understand this, wants to free themselves from the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you do need to know, like, what to ask for, and then it needs to be asked on the right level.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, that's why the instruction of another and utterance of another is necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because people are asking, what is self?
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't necessarily want to abandon the self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... And so, by going in my direction, which I've said, is you always, ah, the self is this amazing, eternal, I am thing that's just indescribable and beyond everything, which it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, in the suttas, often, when people
[SPEAKER_02]: I am that I am.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it is a great... it is a larger phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: True, true.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as if you do not... you want to...
[SPEAKER_00]: The higher self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, the mystical experience is real.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is higher, in a sense, than what your mundane is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's higher than anything else that you can possibly imagine, because it's... everything is within it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you want to be honest, intellectually honest to yourself, can you know a higher self, unless you're experiencing it right here, right now?
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's just hiding its content.
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, it has a less defined content, less mundane content.
[SPEAKER_02]: But in its nature, it's still a reasoned thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why Sotāpanna's understanding is, whatever has the nature of manifesting, that's why it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not, oh, not that he denies that some things manifest at a higher level, some things at a lower.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what everybody said.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever the aggregate, like, whatever matter form, matter feeling, perception, so whatever aggregate is, far or near, low or high, personal, impersonal, present, past, whichever, he understands aggregate of matter is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: He understands aggregative... as in, he understands the nature of phenomenon is present.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter what or on what level.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even if somebody cherishes the sense of I am, unless they forsake the criteria of intellectual honesty, they're still not beyond hope.
[SPEAKER_02]: In terms of, if they want to understand, they still have a basis for that understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can be as mystical as you want, and proliferate your sense of self as far as you wish, and that's not really the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Depends where you're coming from, what you motivate.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you sort of never ever, and you choose that, never ever go in the direction of questioning it, or in questioning yourself in regard to it, that's the worst thing you can do.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you can be ignorant and everything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: You still have a thread of possibility to pull yourself out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you are fully, willingly cemented yourself in your own product of your own wrong view, that's the worst thing you can do.
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, by that I mean, no, no, no, I will not think about that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why would I question the sense of self?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because sense of self is the greatest.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why you question it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't need a reason to question things.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why the Buddha did say that the most blameworthy things
[SPEAKER_02]: In the entire, basically, saṃsāra is the wrong view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nothing else can come on the same level as bad as a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's a direct reason why people do everything else that's unwholesome and that keeps them bound to the to the wanderings and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even if somebody is mystical, I am this, I am this great, I'm this lofty, I have this mystical experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Describe the characteristics of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: You had a mystical experience of this higher self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did you have a say in the manifestation of that?
[SPEAKER_02]: How can you even create something, actually, when you think about it, from that, from nothingness?
[SPEAKER_02]: How can you create something, before which that thing wasn't, and you haven't thought about it, because that would already be that thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're unaware, unknowing, unconscious of this thing, and suddenly you create it.
[SPEAKER_02]: How can that possibly happen?
[SPEAKER_02]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, the experience of the higher self that a person might have had?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I was subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the same sense, I'm subjected to sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, thoughts, ideas, experiences.
[SPEAKER_02]: What are the characteristics of being subjected to these things?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I can't own them even if I want to.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, my lofty mystical experience of a higher self was just another arisen thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because of that, it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because of that,
[SPEAKER_02]: Anicca.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, this great higher sense of self that I had is this lofty...
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, lasted for weeks.
[SPEAKER_02]: I was in this bliss.
[SPEAKER_02]: Cannot be owned.
[SPEAKER_02]: Devalues everything that's based on passion, that's based on wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's... in a way, it's a... it's... that mystic, then, is in a good position, in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's very close.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he just makes a lot of mistakes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Close?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Close or really, really far, depending on the motivation behind his mystical view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mystical view in itself, yeah, it's a wrong view, but it doesn't necessarily mean the person who holds it is like, as I said, beyond repair.
[SPEAKER_02]: He might be quite close, if he's not forsaking that self-questioning, even in regard to his greatest pleasure of his enlightened sense of higher self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if he's abandoning all things,
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's abandoning all things, all things, and then just sort of keeping hold of that great thing in his higher self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the last thing he... And that's why you can see if somebody who is refusing to abandon that too, is actually worse off than somebody who didn't abandon all these things, but hasn't developed that deeply rooted wrong view either.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's rooted in motivation, not necessarily in the content of the view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you abandon that thing, you've abandoned all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, if you abandon that kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, one person abandons the thing that he's supposed to abandon, and the other person abandons everything else...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Except the thing he... And what's that one person that abandons one thing, and the other person don't?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's exactly the difference between sotāpanna and the suttas.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: If somebody has arrived at abandoning all these other things without abandoning the right... the ātavāda, practically speaking,
[SPEAKER_02]: But if one abandons the right thing to begin with, that's actually bad.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because in the long run, you will then arrive at a complete liberation.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the long run, this person won't.
[SPEAKER_02]: If Puthujan abandons sensuality in this life, that's great.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if he abandons sensuality on account of deeply rooting the wrong view of a mystical experience, that's not great.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, his non-sensual behavior in this life can probably result in, you know, better rebirth next time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Coming around, he's going to be in a better position.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, fundamentally, the wrong view will be more and more obscured.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, sooner or later, when that runs out, he's back where he started.
[SPEAKER_02]: While somebody who has understood the Buddha's teaching, who hasn't abandoned sensuality, who hasn't abandoned sensuality yet, but has abandoned the wrong view, means he will have to
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, in a way, he has abandoned it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just that it's sort of fallen off.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, he has uprooted it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why it's important to recognize that when you read the suttas as well, often people get kind of caught up and bogged into content and, oh, this and this side, etc.
[SPEAKER_02]: It needs to be understood on the level of the domains, on the level of the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I have a mystical experience of a lofty self, like you couldn't put it in the words.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, that's your experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: What are the characteristics of that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Stop looking at the content that you couldn't put in the words.
[SPEAKER_02]: Describe the nature of it for yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because there must be something there, otherwise, as I said, speech would not be possible.
[SPEAKER_02]: You wouldn't be able to designate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, originally, we talked about the I, the arising of the I.
[SPEAKER_01]: We talked about the characteristics of the I.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how would you describe someone contemplating arising of the I, passing away of the I?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, contemplating rightly, or somebody trying to figure it out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rightly, rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because, like we said, so, you know, it's quite easy to recognize the arising of a feeling,
[SPEAKER_02]: Whichever way you were to contemplate... well, whatever thing you were to contemplate rightly, as in arising or passing away of it, intensifying or fading away, needs to be done on the right level of generality, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're not on the right level, you... again, you can get to it by trying to do it, but you need to understand that you can only contemplate
[SPEAKER_02]: The arising of the I, the passing away of the I, not by the actual I, but on the level of the experience of the body as a whole, which is the saḷāyatana.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you pointed that out.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's singular.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not six sense bases.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's six sense base.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a base made out of six.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But on the level of base, it's a one base.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a one phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Within that, you can contemplate the direction of the I, the direction of the air, the direction of the... but not at the expense of it
[SPEAKER_02]: But even that...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, practically, practically, the intensification... Intensification of body.
[SPEAKER_02]: The intensification of the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: How did you reveal that?
[SPEAKER_02]: How did you become aware of it?
[SPEAKER_02]: On account of something that's presently enduring on the domain of the visual.
[SPEAKER_02]: Something so impactful, something so significant that you've just seen.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or even just like...
[SPEAKER_01]: I wasn't really...
[SPEAKER_01]: I had my eyes closed,
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Something or other.
[SPEAKER_01]: You then look at... or you suddenly... a bird appears.
[SPEAKER_01]: You suddenly start looking at the bird and you're suddenly more engaged with the visual domain.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you get to discern whether it's arising or ceasing, if you get to discern it peripherally, without even having to attend what you're staring at.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if there is a knowledge of the visual domain, for example, persisting, that's already mindfulness of either arising or either ceasing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, as we established before, neither arising or ceasing is something you are responsible for.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you are responsible in being basically aware, mindful of that which has arising or ceasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the arising and the ceasing is...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, peripherally, not losing the sight, for the lack of a better word, not losing the sight of the visual domain, peripherally, even without paying attention to what you're looking at, that's your gatekeeping of the visual domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, so, those, basically, all of these domains, the eye, the ear, the body, whichever you can even conceive, the five aggregates, all of those things endure
[SPEAKER_01]: And while they're enduring, they're either intensifying or de-intensifying.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a kind of relative sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Relative to each other?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's the wrong way of saying it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's again assuming your timing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Relative means you're comparing the two.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's either like this, or it's either like this.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can't compare.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is going the same speed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, no, the feeling is stronger than the perception then.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recognize that those five things endure, enduring, they're sort of just there.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will be either within themselves, from the perspective of that phenomenon, you will see either this way or that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nothing else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, then, you realize there isn't anything, there doesn't have to be anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess that trying to compare
[SPEAKER_01]: It always assumes a center that you can stand in.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's independent of things that you are comparing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, which is the self-view.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how, usually, people would misunderstand the Buddha, when he would list these things.
[SPEAKER_02]: And he would say, the idea... Ah, so you, like, lay it all out in front of you and then you compare.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how you analyze them and understand them.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you're just maintaining self-view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That would be true if you could truly step outside of yourself, which you can't, which means these things need to be understood on a different level.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why if a logician reads the suttas, you would think, oh, this is just tautology.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: From a logical point of view, it's just mere tautology.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you all laid it out there in itself, evident truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think you don't have to be a logician to...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then the difference is, okay, so what did the Buddha say?
[SPEAKER_02]: If you understand this, what's the result of that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Annihilation of passion and anger, everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, am I ever free from those things?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Means, I'm not understanding it the way that we intended it to be.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, if you don't think that far, then you would end up thinking you understood the suttas, while still not being free from suffering and everything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I have developed an understanding of these things, but that's not what's being spoken about.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: There must be more, because I'm not getting the results that this understanding seems to say you should be having.
It's not like that.